<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Jonathan Moore]]></title><description><![CDATA[Bio data fettling]]></description><link>https://jonathandmoore.github.io</link><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 14:10:22 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jonathandmoore.github.io/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Rhizosphere metatranscriptome analysis]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I&#8217;m a co-investigator on the BBSRC/NERC-funded Roots of Decline project looking at the interactions between crop rotations, rhizosphere microbiome and oilseed rape crop yield.  The project has been tweeting progress <a href="https://twitter.com/BBSRC_SARISA" class="bare">https://twitter.com/BBSRC_SARISA</a> and it&#8217;s been interesting to see the combination of experimental plots, field sampling from farms, and lab work.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We&#8217;ve done some 16S, 18S and ITS analysis on the field samples, and now the first metatranscriptome samples are in library prep for Illumina sequencing, so it&#8217;s time for some fettling.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I took a look at the EBI metagenomics portal, and took some inspiration from their pipeline: <a href="https://www.ebi.ac.uk/metagenomics/about" class="bare">https://www.ebi.ac.uk/metagenomics/about</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My initial plan for our metatranscriptome analysis goes something like this:</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>First the usual <a href="http://earlham.ac.uk" class="bare">http://earlham.ac.uk</a> primary analysis on the data, comprising:</p>
</div>
<div class="literalblock">
<div class="content">
<pre>Demultiplexing with bcl2fastq
   FASTQC
   Kontaminant screening of a random sample of reads, for likely suspects
   MEGAN screening of a random sample of reads, for a taxonomic overview of the sample</pre>
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Providing the quality looks good, we&#8217;ll move on to develop the metatranscriptome analysis.  First a clean-up.</p>
</div>
<div class="literalblock">
<div class="content">
<pre>Trim using Trimmomatic to remove low quality segments and adaptors
   Assemble read paris using PANDAseq (probably)</pre>
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Then comes the first fork in the road. We would like to treat rRNA and mRNA sequence reads differently in the subsequent steps in the analysis.</p>
</div>
<div class="literalblock">
<div class="content">
<pre>Use SortMeRNA to classify sequence reads as rRNA and mRNA</pre>
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There are some complexities with this, as the SortMeRNA rRNA database may not be very sensitive for soil organisms, particularly eukaryotes. There is a lot of underexplored genomic dark matter in the soil, so I&#8217;m told, so we may do some experimenting with various alternative rRNA databases.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Once we have the rRNA/mRNA classification of each molecule nailed down, on to the detailed classifications.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Using rRNA sequences to do taxonomic classification is relatively well explored territory.  We will most likely stick to a Qiime analysis here, but again, we are likely to want to use a specialised database for classification rather than SILVA or GreenGenes.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Classifying mRNA sequences is a bit more tricky.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I recently read that if you ask three different classification methods to classify a sequence read, you are only likely to get two of them to agree on a genus classification about 60% of the time, and only then on reads of 500nt.  Species-level classification is even worse.  Functional classification is even worse still <a href="http://www.nature.com/articles/srep19233" class="bare">http://www.nature.com/articles/srep19233</a>.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>WEVote looks promising in this respect, and I think it&#8217;s a rational approach to taxonomic classification, but I haven&#8217;t had a chance to trying implementing it yet: <a href="http://biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2016/05/22/054205.full.pdf" class="bare">http://biorxiv.org/content/biorxiv/early/2016/05/22/054205.full.pdf</a></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>With that in mind, we will be using a couple of different methods for both taxonomic and functional classification, and correlating the results.  We will also be paying careful attention to the databases we use for the classifications, as this has as much effect, if not more, than the chosen algorithm.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>More later.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>https://jonathandmoore.github.io/2016/09/08/Rhizosphere-metatranscriptome-analysis.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://jonathandmoore.github.io/2016/09/08/Rhizosphere-metatranscriptome-analysis.html</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Jonathan Moore]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>